A Guide to the Czeslawa Zielinska Architectural Collection, 1964-2005, bulk 1966-1979
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Czeslawa Zielinska Architectural Collection, 1964-2005 (Bulk, 1966-1979)
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms2005-017
0.75 cu. ft. 2 boxes; 1 oversize folder
Czeslawa Zielinska is a Polish-born Canadian architect and the inventor the GETSET Building System and, with her husband Zenon, of the UCOPAN, a pre-cast concrete building system. The collection includes promotional material, published articles, and booklets about UCOPAN as well as copies of landscape and building sketches drawn during her travels.
Zielinska, Cz.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
The Czeslawa Zielinska Architectural Collection was donated to the International Archive of Women in Architecture at the Special Collections by its creator in 2005. An addition to the collection was received in 2011.
Biographical Information
Czeslawa (or Czesia) Zielinska is a Polish-born Canadian architect and inventor. She was educated in Poland and holds both a Master of Science degree in Architecture from the Warsaw Technical University in 1952 and a Master of Science in Interior Design from the Academy of Fine Arts in Warsaw in 1962. Zielinska invented the patented GETSET Building System (prefabricated components for building structures and modular furniture), and is co-inventor with her husband, structural engineer Zenon A. Zielinski, of patented UCOPAN (Universal Concrete Panel System). She is a partner in UCOPAN Enterprises and is a member of Royal Institute of Architecture of Canada as well as the Interior Decorators Society of Quebec. Her specialization is in integrated exterior-interior architectural and structural design, low cost housing as well as furniture and product design.
Scope and Content
The collection includes Zielinska's curriculum vitae, a Canadian patent certificate, promotional literature on UCOPAN as well as published papers and articles relevant to UCOPAN's uses and deployment abroad. It also includes personal accounts and photocopies of landscape and building sketches she drew while she and her family were living in Egypt and India from 1966-1971.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged by subject matter, and is divided into Personal Papers, Professional Papers, and Project Records.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Architects and community; International Archive of Women in Architecture (IAWA)
Occupations:
Architects.
Contents List
- Personal Papers, 1964-2005 (Bulk, 1966-1971)
  - Curriculum vitae, patent, biographical notes, diplomas, 1964-2005 (Box-folder 1:1)
  - Sketches [Photocopies], Cairo, Aswan, Alexandria, Egypt and Detroit, 1966-1968, and undated (Box-folder 1:2)
  - Personal Account, Egypt, 1966 (Box-folder 1:3)
  - Personal Account, India, 1968-1971 (Box-folder 1:4)
- Professional Papers, 1970-1979
  - Conference Materials, 1974, 1979 (Box-folder 1:5)
  - GETSET Projects, patents and realized work (Box-folder 2:1)
  - Handbook on Construction of UCOPAN Buildings by Zenon A. Zielinski, January 1970 (Box-folder 2:2)
  - Publications, 1969-1997 (Bulk, 1970-1975)
    - Role of Prefabrication in Low-Cost Housing by Zenon A. Zielinski, part of the publication Papers on Housing put out by Calcutta Metropolitan Planning Organization, 1969 (Box-folder 2:3)
    - Search for Economic and Universal Housing Systems - Some Design and Construction Experience by Zenon A. Zielinski, Oct 1970 (Box-folder 2:4)
    - Demonstration Construction of UCOPAN Houses for Flood Victims at Jalpaiguri, North Bengal, 1970 (Box-folder 2:5)
    - Article in Decormag, June 1975 (Box-folder 2:6)
    - Article in the Journal of the Prestressed Concrete Institute, May/June 1982 (Box-folder 2:7)
    - Promotional Material on GETSET and UCOPAN, ca. 1973 - 1997 (Box-folder 2:8)
- Project Records, 1985-2005 (Bulk, 1985-1987)
  - Cour St. Marc condominium Montreal, 1987 (Box-folder 2:9-10)
  - UCOPAN Barbados: Housing Design, 1985-2005 (Box-folder 2:11)